[{"question":"<p><strong>A key characteristic of the civil service is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Merit system","Patriotism","Quota system","Transparency"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A major cause of inefficiency in public corporations is&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Inadequate patronage by members of the public","Absence of an enabling Act or law","Political interference","Competition from private firms"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A major distinction between public corporations and private companies is that<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Public corporations provide important services","Public corporations are large organizations","Public corporations are financed and controlled by government","Public corporations are not involved in production of tangible goods"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A primary agency of political socialization is:&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The government","The family","The mass media","The School"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A process that seeks to transfer ownership and control of public corporations to private&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>individuals or organizations is called&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Indigenization","Commercialization","Privatization","Acquisition"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Adult male suffrage means that&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["All men who pay tax can vote.","All adult males can vote.","All men can vote.","All adults can vote."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>All of the following are obligations of citizens, except&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Obedience to laws.","Voting.","Giving alms to beggars.","Payment of taxes."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>An electoral district is&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["A local government area.","A ward.","A polling booth.","A constituency."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Fascism was practiced in Italy under:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Benito Masollini","Benito Mubarak","Benito Mussolini","Benito Mandela"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Governmental powers are _________&nbsp;in the US presidential system&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Absolutely separated","Fused","Absolutely fused","Separated"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In a democracy, franchise is limited by&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Age","Sex","Wealth.","Education."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In the civil service, anonymity means that civil servants must&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Not receive the credit or blame for any good.","Serve any government impartially","Avoid nepotism and favouritism.","Be politically neutral."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In which of the following set of countries is a dominant two-party system operated.&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Nigeria and Ghana.","The United States and the United Kingdom.","France and Germany.","India and China."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the advantages of direct election is that:&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["It is too expensive and difficult to conduct","Illiterates vote intelligently for their leaders","It makes representatives accountable to the electors","It offers an opportunity to the electorate to demand for money"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the following is not a feature of a modern state<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Territorial landmass","Population of People","Defined Territory","Sovereignty"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the following is not a source of constitution?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Customs and conventions","Civil service regulations","Historical documents","Judicial precedents."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the objectives of a multiparty system is to &nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Eliminate corruption","Prevent rigging.","Provide alternatives.","Avoid ethnicity"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Political sovereignty lies with:&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Head of State","Head of Government","The Parliament","The electorate"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Public corporations are established principally to&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Compete with private firms","Raise revenue for the government","Provide essential services for the public","Promote public Accountability"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Public opinion helps a government to&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Monitor its socio-cultural policy","Monitor the economic situation in the country.","Punish opposition to its policies.","Develop the country in line with the people\u0092s aspirations."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Roles that are expected to be performed by an individual in a country are<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Elections","Duties.","Rights.","Services."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Separation of powers denotes __________________<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Separation of governmental powers but not separation of persons","Separation of governmental powers and Separation of persons","Separation of persons only","Separation of powers of government only"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The assent of the President is required to convert a\/an ____ to law<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Bill","Edict","Proclamation","Decree"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The branch of Government that sets agenda for other organs is known as:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The bureaucracy","The legislature","The executive","The mass media"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The capitalist economy is dictated by:&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Government economic blueprint","Consumers\u0092 requirements","Diminishing returns","The forces of demand and supply"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The central Legislative body in Britain is referred to as _______________<\/strong><\/p>","options":["National Assembly","Knesset","Parliament","Congress"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The chairman of the committee that reviewed the 1988 civil service commission was<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Chief P.C Asiodu.","Chief Edwin Clerk.","Chief Allison Ayida.","Chief Simeon Adebo."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The highest grade in the civil service is known as&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Executive cadre","Administrative cadre.","Technical cadre.","Clerical cadre."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The law of libel limits a citizen&rsquo;s right to freedom of&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Association","Expression","Worship.","Movement."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The major advantage of the secret ballot is that&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["It ensures the anonymity of each voter.","It is faster than other systems","Nobody can be prevented from voting","It extends  the franchise to all adults."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The permanent executive includes:&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Civil servants and not public servants","Civil servants and politicians","All career officers that serve any government in power","Elected and appointed politicians"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The pressure group that resorts to unconventional methods to achieve its objectives is called<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Institutional group","Interest group","Promotional group","Anomic group"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The three fundamental rights of citizens are&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Life, liberty and property","Salvation, property, freedom of thought.","Employment, property and social security.","Free education, employment and property."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>When a constitution is not difficult to amend, it is said to be:&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Rigid","Systematic","Flexible","Federal"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following best describes a sovereign state?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["A member of the African Union","Freedom from economic control","Geographical contiguity","Military, political and economic independence"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of these is an element of state power?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Geographical location, population & economic resources","Geographical location, elite interests & economic resources","Geographical location, ethnicity & economic resources","Geographical location, political crisis & economic resources"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of these is not a method of election? &nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Simple majority","Proportional representation","Primary election","Co-option."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>___________ plays rule adjudication role in Nigeria<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The Civil Service","The Legislature","The Executive","The Judiciary"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A two-party system of government is one in which<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Only one party performs multiparty functions","The elite dominate political parties","Only few parties are allowed to operate by law","There are two major parties and other minor parties"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>An important agency for social control in the Igbo traditional society was the&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Age-grade","Ozo-title holders.","Council of Chiefs.","Assembly of lineage heads."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Educated elites in Nigeria did not like the system of indirect rule because it&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Did not make provisions for them","Was exploitative and cumbersome.","Made traditional rulers too powerful.","Was undemocratic and oppressive."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Federalism in Nigeria is best seen as a way of promoting&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Rapid economic development","Unity in diversity","Even national development","Democracy"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In Nigeria, the civil service was first regionalized by the&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Independence constitution","Richard constitution","Clifford constitution","Lyttleton constitution"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In the Hausa pre-colonial political system, sovereignty was located in the&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Alkali","Emir","Waziri","Galadima"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In the pre-Colonial Hausa\/Fulani system, the appointment of an Emir in the caliphate was&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>approved by<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Sultan of Sokoto and the Emir of Gwandu.","Galadima and the Waziri.","Sardauna of Sokoto and the Alkali.","Sheu of Bornu and the Galadima."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Nationalist activities in British West Africa increased after the second World War because&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Of the expulsion of Kwane Nkrumah from Britain.","Of the return of the educated elite from abroad","Prices of commodities fell below expectation","Africans were nominated to the executive council."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Nigeria started to operate a real federal structure with the introduction of the&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["1922 Clifford constitution.","1946 Richard constitution.","1953 London conference.","1954 Lytelton constitution."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Nigeria&rsquo;s First Constitution&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Lytelton constitution","Clifford constitution.","Macpherson Constitution.","Independence constitution."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the fundamental changes recommended by Adedotun Philips commission is&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Frequent movement of staff","Standardization","Professionalization","Stagnation"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the fundamental reversals made by the commission that reviewed the 1988 reform of&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>the civil service was.&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Change of Director General to Permanent Secretaries.","Change from Permanent Secretary to Director General.","Change from Director General to Permanent Administrators.","Permanent Professionals."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The ________ Local government reforms recognized local government as the third tier of&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>government<\/strong><\/p>","options":["1963","1976","1988","1989"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The breakdown of the Macpherson constitution was partly caused by the crisis within the&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["NCNC","AG","NPC","NNDP"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The First Executive president of Nigeria was<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Dr. Nnamdi Azikiwe.","Sir Abubakar Tafawa Balewa","General Yakubu Gowon","Alhaji Sheu Shagari"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The first military coup in Nigeria took place on ________<\/strong><\/p>","options":["July 15, 1966","July 27, 1967","January 15, 1966","January 13, 1966"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The first three political parties to be registered in the Fourth Republic were&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["ACN, ANPP and PDP","AD, APP and PDP","PPA, PDP, CAN","APGA, CAN and PDPB"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The imposition of unitary form of administration by General Ironsi in 1966 led to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["More military institutions","Return to civilian rule","Independence from British rule","Civil unrest in the North"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The institution that preserves civil liberty in Nigeria is the&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Law Court.","Civil Service Commission.","Police Affairs Commission.","Public Complaints Commission."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The main opposition party during the First Republic was the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Northern Peoples Congress","Action Group","Northern Element Progressive Union","United Middle Belt Congress"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The state created in Nigeria before 1966 was<\/strong><\/p>","options":["East central state","Lagos state","Mid- Western state","North central state"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The1964 federal election was contested by two major alliances of political parties among&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>these:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["All Progressive Grand Alliance and the Northern Peoples Alliance","Nigerian National Alliance and United Progressive Grand Alliance","National Democratic Coalition and Nigerian Peoples Alliance","National Democratic Alliance and Northern Elements Progressive Union"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Under the 1999 constitution of the Federal Republic of Nigeria there are a total of ________&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>Local government councils<\/strong><\/p>","options":["334","620","724","774"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following ethnic groups had the best egalitarian traditional political system?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Hausa\/ Fulani.","Yoruba.","Igbo.","Edo."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is not a major problem of local government in Nigeria&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Insufficient funding and limited internally generated revenue","Interference and control by higher levels of government","Lack of competent and qualified staff","Lack of sufficient number of local government"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is not a reason for the adoption of a Federal System of government? ________<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Cultural diversities","Security consideration","Economic consideration","Limited resources."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is not an example of a public corporation in Nigeria&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Nigerian Railway Corporation","Federal Radio Corporation of Nigeria","Federal Mortgage Bank of Nigeria","National Deposit Insurance Corporation"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following statements is true about the 1963 and 1979 Constitutions<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Both had provisions for the office of the president","Both had provision for the office of the constitutional president.","Both provided for the offices of prime minister and president.","Both had provision for the office of an executive president."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of these former Nigerian Heads of State was instrumental to the establishment of&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>ECOWAS?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Sanni Abacha","Yakubu Gowon","Olusegun Obasanjo","Tafawa Balewa"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In 1975, Nigeria had a strained relationship with one of the following countries over the crisis&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>in Angola.<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Britain","Israel","USA","Mexico"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Nigeria&rsquo;s non &ndash; aligned posture was criticized on ground of the&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Non \u0096 Proliferation Treaty","ECOWAS Treaty","Nuclear Test Ban Treaty","Anglo \u0096 Nigeria Defence Pact"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The circumstance that led to the establishment of ECOWAS Monitoring Group (ECOMOG ) was<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The bloody civil war in Nigeria","The bloody civil war in Liberia","The bloody civil war in Sudan","The bloody civil war in all West African countries"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The head of Nigeria&rsquo;s foreign mission in a Commonwealth nation is best known and addressed&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Ambassador","Envoy","High commissioner","Representative"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>What determines Nigeria&rsquo;s relations with other countries?&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Its national interest","Its level of democratization","Its citizens political sagacity","Its political culture"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following best defines foreign policy?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The ways in which some actors on the domestic scene translate available power into policies designed to bring positive outcomes","The actions of a state towards the celestial environment","A set of objectives with regards to the world beyond the borders of a given state and a set of strategies and tactics designed to achieve these objectives","The protection of the territorial integrity of a state"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following military regimes was credited with a dynamic foreign policy?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Gowon administration","Murtala Mohammed administration","Sani Abacha regime","Abubakar regime"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of these is correct about Nigeria&rsquo;s foreign policy between 1960 and 1966&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["It was pro-British","It was pro-American","It was pro-Soviet","It was pro-French"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of these is NOT part of a country&rsquo;s core or vital interests&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Economic viability","Political independence","Territorial integrity","Political brouhaha"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of these is NOT the essence of foreign policy?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Promotion and defence of a nation\u0092s vital interest","Protection and promotion of a nation\u0092s strategic interest","Protection and promotion of the interest of the political leaders of a country","Promotion and defence of the economic interest of a nation"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of these Nigerians has ever played a leading role in the operation of OPEC?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Alhaji Rilwanu Lukman","Prof Joe Garba","Prof Joy Ogwu","Gen. Ike Nwachukwu"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which year was the Anglo-Nigerian defence pact abrogated?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["1962","1963","1960","1961"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A major weakness of the Commonwealth is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Lack of commitment by member states","Lack of quorum at annual summits","Poverty among member states","Lack of democratic Leadership"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>An essential principle that guides the works of the United Nations&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The regulation of international trade","The protection of the United States of America against terrorism","Respect for sovereign equality of member states","The transfer of technology to developing Countries"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In which of these International Organisations is African membership NOT possible?&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["ECOWAS","EU","OPEC","Commonwealth"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Membership of the Commonwealth of Nations means&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Recognition of the Queen as the Head of the commonwealth and the republican states","Recognition of the Queen as the Head of the commonwealth and not of the Republican States","Recognition of the Queen as the Head of the independent states and the republican states","Recognition of the Queen as the Head of all independent states"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>One major achievement of OPEC is that&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Member nations are now formidable forces to be reckoned with in international politics","World economic depression brought about fall in oil price","Here is a declining loyalty of its members","There are challenges posed by non \u0096 OPEC members"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the following groups of states are all members of the ECOWAS<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Nigerian Ghana and Zaire","Guinea, Togo and Cameroun","Guinea Bissau, Burkina Faso and Cape Verde","Liberia Benin and Ethiopia"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The AU was formed by members of OAU&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["On 8th July 2002 at Durban, South Africa","On 8th July 2003 at Abuja, Nigeria","On 8th July 2003 at Tripoli","On 8th June 2002 at Accra, Ghana"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The first nation to become a republic within the Commonwealth of Nations is&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Nigeria","Cyprus","Ghana","India"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The first summit of the African Union (AU) took place&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["On February 2, 2004 at Addis Ababa, Ethiopia","On February 3, 2003 at Addis Ababa, Ethiopia","On February 3, 2003 at Abuja, Nigeria","On February 2, 2004 at Lagos, Nigeria"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The Non-aligned Movement was established at__________ in _________.&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Bombay, 1955","Bandung, 1955","Lagos, 1972","Addis Ababa, 1955"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The OAU adopted NEPAD during its summit held in&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Abuja","Lusaka","Tunis","Cairo"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The organ charged with the responsibility of approving the annual budget of UNO is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The Security Council","The International Court of Justice","The General Assembly","The Trusteeship Council"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>To which of these blocs did Nigeria belong before the establishment of the OAU?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Casablanca group","Monrovia group","Pan African group","African and Malagasy group"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>What is the full meaning of ECOWAS?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Economic Community for Western African States","Economic Community of Western African States","Economic Community of West African States","Economic Community for West African States"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Where and when was the African Union inaugurated?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Durban, 2000","Addis Ababa 1963","Lagos, 1972","Tripoli, 2001"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is a functionally specialized global international organization&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Organization of African Unity","United Nations","Food and Agriculture Organization","African Union"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is a specialized agency of the AU?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The Assembly Conference","The  Executive Council","African Court of Justice","The Commission"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is an apt definition of the Commonwealth of Nations?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Voluntary  association of the independent countries of the former British Colonies","Association of free nations enjoying equal rights under the British","A free association of sovereign independent African States","A voluntary association of countries that were formerly in the French colonial empire"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is NOT a principal organ of the UNO?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["UNICEF","Security Council","Secretariat","General Assembly"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following metamorphosed into the United Nations?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["International Labour Organization","League of Nations","UNESCO","OAU"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The N.C.N.C sent a delegation to London in 1947 to protest against the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["burns constitution","Richards constitution","Littleton constitution","Macpherson constitution"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p>Representative democracy is best characteristic by<\/p>","options":["Free elections and proper registers of voters","A politically educated electorate","Rule by the interest group","Proper constituencies and a real choice of candidates"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p>While political partial parties aim at forming a<br \/>government pressure groups aim at<\/p>","options":["Causing social unrest","Influencing governmental decisions","Controlling nation\u0092s economy","Getting workers to unite"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p>When the electorate vote for representatives who is<br \/>turn vote on their behalf we say it is<\/p>","options":["An indirect election","An unfair election","A disputed election","A rigged electron"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p>An election which is conducted to fill a vacant seat in a<br \/>legislature is called a<\/p>","options":["By election","General election","Referendum","Plebiscite"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p>Which of these countries does NOT operate a federal<br \/>constitution?<\/p>","options":["USA","Nigeria","Canada","France"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p>The major advantage of the secret ballot is that<\/p>","options":["It is faster than other systems","Nobody can be prevented from voting","It ensures the anonymity of each voter","Losers can ask for another secret voter"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p>In a one party state<\/p>","options":["There are no free citizens","The communist party is the only legal party","The ruling party is the only legal party","Elections to be legislature are held at the party\u0092s conferences"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p>A cabinet system of government is practiced in<\/p>","options":["Britain and Canada","The soviet union","All European Countries including Britain","The United State of America"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p>A proclamation by the head of state ending a session<br \/>of parliament is called<\/p>","options":["A dissolution","An adjournment","A prorogation","A devolution"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p>The constitution of the federal republic of Nigeria<\/p>","options":["Promotes unity of diversity","Allows for the dominance of the minority ethnic groups","Concentrates governmental power at on one level of government","Ensures the dominance of one political party"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p>The transfer of authority to local government council<br \/>is known as<\/p>","options":["Delegation","Fusion","Fragmentation","Devolution"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p>The principle of anonymity of civil servants means<br \/>that they<\/p>","options":["Are not the servant of a particular government","Are trained for the duties they perform","Are credited or blamed for any thing they do","Have a career"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p>The six registered political parties in Nigeria in 1982<br \/>were<\/p>","options":["UPN, NPN, PPA, PPP, NPP, and NAP","UPN, GNPP, NAP, PRP, NPP, NPN","NPN, UPN, NPP, PRP, PPP NNDP","NPC, GNPP, PRP, UPN, NPP and PPA"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p>Which of the following is NOT a pressure group in<br \/>Nigeria<\/p>","options":["Farmers","the Nigerian union of teachers (NUT)","Nigeria medical associate (NMA)","Academic staff union of university (ASUU)"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p>The N.C.N.C sent a delegation to London in 1947 to<br \/>protest against the<\/p>","options":["Burns constitution","Richards constitution","Littleton constitution","Macpherson constitution"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p>A popular principle of colonial administration in British<br \/>west Africa was<\/p>","options":["Association","Indirect rule","Paternalism","Assimilation"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p>The first governor-general of colonial Nigeria was<\/p>","options":["Sir, Hugh Clifford","Sir James Robertson","Lord Lugard","Sir Ralph moore"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p>The first military government in Nigeria was headed<br \/>by<\/p>","options":["General Yakubu Gowon","General Agunyi Ironsi","General M. Mohammed","General O. Obasanjo"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p>The first general election in Nigeria was hold in<\/p>","options":["1933","1952","1955","1959"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"}]